<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>I'm Thad.</title>
    <subtitle>I make things.</subtitle>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/" />
    <link rel="self" href="https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/feed.xml" type="application/atom+xml" />
    <id>https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/</id>
    <updated>2021-02-06T14:32:30Z</updated>

    <author>
        <name>Thad Hughes</name>
        <email>hughes.thad@gmail.com</email>
        <uri>https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/</uri>
    </author>

    
        <entry>
            <title>Arithmetic Thinking is Smoothbrained.</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/geometric/" type="text/html" />
            <id>https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/geometric/</id>
            <updated>2021-02-06T03:31:13Z</updated>

            <summary type="html">The development of early western philosophy is undoubtedly intertwined with mathematics, and in particular, geometry.</summary>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The development of early western philosophy is undoubtedly intertwined with mathematics, and in particular, geometry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may recall from your math classes, or from calculus two, geometric series and arithmetic series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;geometric&lt;/em&gt; series is one where the next number is some constant &lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt; (a ratio, or proportion) of the previous, e.g.:
&lt;code&gt;1, 3, 9, 27, 81, 243&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;arithmetic&lt;/em&gt; series is one where the next number is some constant &lt;em&gt;additive&lt;/em&gt; of the previous, e.g.:
&lt;code&gt;2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/assets/images/geo_arith_plot.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the typical mathematics course will help remind you of how these work by creating stories such as &amp;ldquo;One Grain of Rice&amp;rdquo;, the relation is actually inverse- the story emerges from the series, not the series from the story. The geometric series has many manifestations, all of which could be considered natural, from the Latin &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;nasci&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, meaning to give birth. One begets two, the two beget four, the four beget eight; a flowering out by which the entire space may be filled even as the originals die off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arithmetic sequence, on the other hand, is a sterile one, a steady march by which gains are made begrudgingly and uninterestingly, if at all. There are no network effects. This does not describe a natural process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this is further reflected by the etymology of these terms. Both terms have their origins in greek: &amp;lsquo;geometry&amp;rsquo;, or &lt;em&gt;γεομετρια&lt;/em&gt; (γε &amp;lsquo;earth&amp;rsquo;, μετρια &amp;lsquo;measure&amp;rsquo;) regarding the surveying of land and nature; &amp;lsquo;arithmetic&amp;rsquo; or &lt;em&gt;αριθμητικη&lt;/em&gt; (art of counting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The error of the arithmetic mindset is made even more apparent when we flip the progression in the other direction, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geometric series: &lt;code&gt;1, 1/2, 1/4, 1/8, 1/16&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arithmetic series: &lt;code&gt;1, 0, -1, -2, -3...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as describing physical phenomena, the former makes much more sense than the latter: negative quantities do not exist, or at least, are unsustainable debts which must be repaid. The geometric series, however, can infinitely collapse and converge upon an essential truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interactions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take this into two dimensions. A dimension is simply an orthogonal axis, an axis that varies independently of the first. Let&amp;rsquo;s consider the ratio 2 for some geometric series and arithmetic series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geometric: &lt;code&gt;A = 2, 4, 8, 16, 32; B = 3, 6, 12, 24, 48&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arithmetic: &lt;code&gt;A = 2, 4, 6, 8, 10; B = 3, 5, 7, 9, 11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can visualize the effects that these two dimensions have on each other if we consider them as lengths of the legs of a right triangle. If you have some graph paper, feel free to plot it for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the geometric series, the ratio progresses from 2:3 to 32:48 (which, if you notice, reduces to 2:3). The proportion, or shape remains the same. In the arithmetic series the ratio progresses from 2:3 to 10:11, or in decimal terms, from about 0.66 to 0.90909.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were to continue these series on, both do indeed continue growing unceasingly, but the ratios diverge. The geometric ratio always remains constant. However, with an arithmetic ratio, the ratio converges to unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion A: If all dimensions are geometric, the relationship between them does not change.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion B: If all dimensions are arithmetic, the relationship between them changes, and approaches, but never converges to, unity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keen eye would see that there are more possibilities, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion C: If one dimension is geometric, and the other arithmetic, the relationship between them diverges, in favor of the geometric.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From series analysis we know that this is true even if the ratio for the arithmetic is higher than the geometric. The arithmetic may have a short-run advance if its ratio is sufficiently high, but there is some point at which it dominates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where are we going with this? Early ‘western’ (modern &amp;lsquo;near east&amp;rsquo;) thinkers recognized the link between morality and beauty- and as such, were keen to the link that morality would have with proportion. It has been said that sin is an aspiration to that which is not possible- mirroring the approaching-but-not-converging nature of an arithmetic-arithmetic ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Politics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The co-option of the term &amp;lsquo;progressive&amp;rsquo; by some politicians and progressives is quite regrettable, as we can clearly see now there are many ways in which to &amp;lsquo;progress&amp;rsquo;. Save for the anti-natalists, verily, all people desire progression, at least in the form of begetting replacement offspring. The question is, by which algorithm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aristotle advocates for a geometric progress: &amp;ldquo;for if persons are unequal, they ought not have equal shares&amp;rdquo;; unequal shares for unequal merit. 10 times 3 is 30, a +20 increase. 100 times 3 is 300, a +200 increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The egalitarian, however, advocates for arithmetic progress: equal shares, regardless of merit. 10 plus 3 is 13, and 100 plus 3 is 103.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this many practical ideas can be plainly illustrated (suppose, say, one modifies the sequence so one can influence their standing in the sequence- in a geometric progression, their efforts are multiplied and rewarded, whereas in an arithmetic progression, they are discarded and ignored). But the key really is a sense of proportion, and that there is good beyond the mere growth of a sequence. A geometric scheme allows for a sense of beauty and proportion that emerges not from the mere magnitude of numbers, but their relationship and harmony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may at blush sound like &amp;lsquo;slave morality&amp;rsquo; as Nietzsche might describe it (accepting a lower position out of a trick the upper classes play), but it clearly is nonsensical as this same sort of thinking benefits the &amp;lsquo;masters&amp;rsquo; as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way out is not in a rat race of arithmetic progression, but in respect for divine proportion and the opportunities that multiplication offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riffing on conclusion C, the arithmetic mindset is ultimately doomed if not alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The geometric mindset, being natural, cannot be extinguished- only ran foolishly against. &amp;ldquo;Whoever has will be given more, and they will have an abundance. Whoever does not have, even what they have will be taken from them.&amp;rdquo; - Matthew 13:12&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;3 → 6 → 12 → 24 → 48&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;-1 → -2 → -4 → -16 → -32&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arithmetic sympathizers do have one option, though, and that is to eliminate all traces of geometric progression. It is only in the utter rejection of all proportion and ratio that the arithmetic approach can stand any chance. It may at times &amp;lsquo;embrace&amp;rsquo; a geometric sense of beauty, but it will seek to add and &amp;lsquo;extend&amp;rsquo; (extension is clearly a different process than multiplication), and ultimately &amp;lsquo;extinguish&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Golden Ratio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arithmetic thinkers will often criticize the present distributions. They will rarely criticize the ratios, but instead focus on absolute discrepancies. The acknowledgement of ratio is itself a geometric idea. You may be well familiar with one such &amp;lsquo;golden ratio&amp;rsquo;, approximately 1.618, often by the symbol &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/assets/images/phi.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She’s beautiful, isn’t she?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delight of this ratio is that squares of proportionately larger diameter can be arranged together to form a structure without gaps. It is not only geometric thinking that enables this, but also the correct proportion. The role of the geometric thinker cannot be merely to rebuke the arithmetic-minded, but to show them that a ratio which could accomplish just ends does exist. I do not argue that there is something about φ which is imbued in every circumstance- &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt; happens to work for packing boxes in this fashion (among other recursive patterns), but will not work for all problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only ratio which the arithmetic-minded can comprehend is one-to-one, and even that, they must at some point recognize as unstable at best and impossible at worst. The rigidity of their ratio disallows any natural flourishing in nearly all cases. Nothing natural has a ratio of one. Even the ameoba can reproduce multiple times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, fine. There is something neat about &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;, or at least the concept it represents. It&amp;rsquo;s the magical ratio such that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;φ = a/b = (a+b)/a&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a ratio that allows for spiraling down (or up). It represents the idea that the same proportion exists amongst the small things as amongst the large things. That is to say, that you expect to see similar patterns on a macro- as a micro- scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Room for Imagination&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably have heard of the &lt;em&gt;Cult of Pythagoras&lt;/em&gt;. These swell fellows were of the belief that all numbers could be represented as integers, or fractions thereof. We today would call these &lt;em&gt;rational&lt;/em&gt; numbers. It&amp;rsquo;s plain to see how would would imagine they could exist. Heresy, to these fellows, came in when geometry was introduced. We&amp;rsquo;re familiar with the pythagorean theorem,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;a^2 + b^2 = c^2&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The sum of the squares of a right triangle&amp;rsquo;s legs equals the sum of it&amp;rsquo;s hypotenuse.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we know now that the solutions to &lt;code&gt;y = x^2&lt;/code&gt; are of the form &lt;code&gt;x = sqrt(y)&lt;/code&gt;, which are generally &lt;em&gt;irrational&lt;/em&gt; numbers. They cannot be represented as fractions. Indeed, the poor arithmetic-minded cultists of pythagoras could not take the leap of faith required to accept an &lt;em&gt;irrational&lt;/em&gt; solution even when the necessity stared them in the face. We see this today in new-atheist types, who having reduced the world so far down to an essential motive force that you could call God, refuse to call it God or at least treat it as such. Their a priori &amp;lsquo;rational&amp;rsquo; framework doesn&amp;rsquo;t allow them the freedom for such concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geometric thinkers, even if they did not admit that the square root of 5 was a number, would nonetheless admit that the side length of a hypotenuse was &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;, existent, and useful to speak of. We see this a lot in the post-new-atheist types (e.g. Peterson), who recognize that you must call it God, even if not canonical and real in the same sense the rest of reality is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The geometric mindset is a playful one which seeks the unknown and mystical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Manifestations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still not sure what I&amp;rsquo;m getting at? Here&amp;rsquo;s a cheat sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geometric:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flourishing (&amp;ldquo;flowering out&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The traditional family across multiple generations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reinvestment of labor and wealth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spread of ideas by network effects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning from tradition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Big Bang&amp;rdquo; theory (or Creationism)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charity and free sowing of seed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arithmetic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sustinence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replacement populations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universal Income&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extraction of surplus value; usury&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ignorance of history&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steady-state universe theory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stinginess and hoarding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; among many more examples. You have a brain. Think geometrically, and all will be clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you think of other schemes than geometric and arithmetic? Sure! I invite you to think of them. I’d be interested to see your parallels.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>The Web is a Real Place.</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/web_as_realworld/" type="text/html" />
            <id>https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/web_as_realworld/</id>
            <updated>2021-02-06T03:23:51Z</updated>

            <summary type="html">For years now people have been trying to &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.substack.com/p/welcome-facebook-and-twitter-seriously&#34;&gt;fix the internet&lt;/a&gt;. Not a lot of people are talking about modeling and understanding the internet in the first place, though. A lot of folk like myself have a sort of &amp;lsquo;nostalgia&amp;rsquo; for the &amp;lsquo;old internet&amp;rsquo;. That&amp;rsquo;s a nebulous statement, but it&amp;rsquo;s right. To understand, an analogue is needed.</summary>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For years now people have been trying to &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.substack.com/p/welcome-facebook-and-twitter-seriously&#34;&gt;fix the internet&lt;/a&gt;. Not a lot of people are talking about modeling and understanding the internet in the first place, though. A lot of folk like myself have a sort of &amp;lsquo;nostalgia&amp;rsquo; for the &amp;lsquo;old internet&amp;rsquo;. That&amp;rsquo;s a nebulous statement, but it&amp;rsquo;s right. To understand, an analogue is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internet is a &lt;em&gt;realm&lt;/em&gt; which has &lt;em&gt;places&lt;/em&gt;. Much like reality consists of physical places. They have rules and behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You, saavy internet user, are walking through this realm right now. As of this writing, this domain points to a set of files hosted on github (via their github pages service). I&amp;rsquo;ve got my own address (a domain, thadhughes.xyz). I also have a P.O. box (my email, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:hughes.thad@gmail.com&#34;&gt;hughes.thad@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;). I don&amp;rsquo;t have a mailbox yet; I haven&amp;rsquo;t set up a mail server at the domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People online are generally in very strange living situations. Most people don&amp;rsquo;t even have an address. They have P.O. boxes (emails) and are in homeless shelters (such as Facebook, Twitter, YouTube). The &amp;ldquo;successful&amp;rdquo; folks, with tons of subscribers, are just getting out of the shelters- they are starting to make money but still living on the generosity of platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They don&amp;rsquo;t own their platform. The notion that these e-celebs &amp;ldquo;have&amp;rdquo; a platform is absurd. They&amp;rsquo;re on one, but they don&amp;rsquo;t have one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The random programmer with their own website is infinitely more soveirgn than a famous YouTuber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what was it about the &amp;lsquo;old internet&amp;rsquo; that we&amp;rsquo;re nostalgic about? What marked it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interactivity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One sign was less interactivity, and more personality. &amp;ldquo;Bob posted on your wall&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;Bob put a political candidate&amp;rsquo;s sign in front of your bed&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;Bob sent you an email&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;Bob sent you a letter&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;Bob came and talked to you&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often think that a more &amp;lsquo;interactive&amp;rsquo; world is better. And it is- it is better to be active in the world. But the &amp;lsquo;interaction&amp;rsquo; that we typically have is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/8754425-a-surrogate-activity-is-an-activity-that-is-directed-toward&#34;&gt;surrogate&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;re employing a system to be our messenger instead of being personal. Like corporate gift baskets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to return to a less interactive internet. Shut down the comment boxes. Open your email composer, or IM, or SMS, or just pick up the phone already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sending a message or an email may be awkward. But don&amp;rsquo;t you love those little suprises that come in your email out of nowhere? They&amp;rsquo;re so much better than corporate gift baskets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Soveirgnty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are things which a man should be able to control and be soveirgn in. If he cannot be soveirgn in his speech, he has forfeited his soul. I mean that. If he is subject to terms of service in the words he puts forth, they are inherently limited and he lacks the capacity to speak freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only in content, but in form, too. All facebook pages are the same. All twitter pages are the same. Remember MySpace? Remember the old YouTube layouts? There was so much diversity in how you could lay out your page and rearrange it. There was a degree of soveirgnty in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was it ugly? Absolutely. And that was fantastic. There was room to be gaudy, to be expressive. It made those that managed the medium and created beauty that much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you&amp;rsquo;re not the customer, you&amp;rsquo;re not the soveirgn. You will be subject to increasing conformity and blandness and a narrowing of forms until all is squeezed out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Protocols, not platforms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember IRC? Ok, maybe you don&amp;rsquo;t. Remember email? Yeah, of course you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email isn&amp;rsquo;t a platform. Google can&amp;rsquo;t just shut down email. They could shut down gmail, but other email providers would still exist. Even with gmail, you can still connect Outlook to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to use Instagram? You have to use Instagram. And if you want to post, you have to do it from a phone (or spoof your web browser to act like a phone). You&amp;rsquo;re not going outside. You&amp;rsquo;re locked in. There&amp;rsquo;s no migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re going out in public you might frequent different places. But you don&amp;rsquo;t put on a different outfit to enter every single different establishment. You have your own sense of style and utility. Not everyone pays with card, some pay with cash. If you don&amp;rsquo;t like how one place is doing business you up and leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other areas, admittedly, we&amp;rsquo;ve gotten better. HTML5 blows the socks off Flash and Java (like, Java applets) in this category. (I&amp;rsquo;ll acknowledge wins when I see them!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RSS is a weird middle ground. Which brings us to the next point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Memberships Maybe, F&amp;amp;@% Feeds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Unpaid) subscriptions and feeds are a stain on our lives. This is literally the modern day equivalent of junk mail and I don&amp;rsquo;t think you can convince me otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to the first point about interactivity- do you keep a list of your friends, and message them every day? No, you message as things come up or you think of ideas. You riff. Things have highs and lows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should seek out particular ideas. Not be fed some constant stream. The idea of having someone constantly streaming ideas at you originated with whoever came up with junk mail, and never before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paid memberships are different. It goes back to the basic principle that you pay for things that have value. The payment forces you to assess the quality of that which you are given, and encourages you to cut it out when it&amp;rsquo;s no longer useful. In this way, paying for things is beneficial to you.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>The Three S&#39;s</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/threess/" type="text/html" />
            <id>https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/threess/</id>
            <updated>2020-09-29T03:05:00Z</updated>

            <summary type="html">When I mentored FLL, I came up with three design principles that I could instill in my students. It seemed to take root. The three S&amp;rsquo;s:
- Simple
- Solid
- Servicable</summary>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I mentored FLL, I came up with three design principles that I could instill in my students. It seemed to take root. The three S&amp;rsquo;s:
- Simple
- Solid
- Servicable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy expounding and talking about how to improve systems at length, but this pnemonic instills some fundamentals of good design. It&amp;rsquo;s not inherent to mechanical, or electric, or software design&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s just good principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Simple&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything should be made simple. This has many benefits: the system can be better understood, and thus improved. Parts count, and thusly cost, goes down. For me this often means eschewing libraries and complex mechanisms when a simpler custom one will do. Use one large bracket, not multiple smaller ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Solid&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything should be robust and stand up to abuse. This should be self explanatory. But this also means looking for edge cases, and surviving them. This means testing all possible load scenarios, finding the dirty edge cases in software, and really understanding the full range of conditions your system could be subjected to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Servicable&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, things will go wrong. We ought to be willing to recognize this and plan ahead, making sure that we, and our end users, can fix things in a timely and frustration-free manner when they do. This means providing clearance around fasteners, taking time to care about assembly order, routing wires so they can be accessed, and yes, documenting your design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Shipped&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas, all good trinities face the problem that Jung cited: that of three versus four. The three in their unity seem to form an idealization, but as they come to fruition, a problem arises, and a compensatory fourth is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, what you&amp;rsquo;re building needs to be done and shipped. Dwelling too long on these principles, optimizing, will lead you to the deadline unfinished. Real artists ship. This means eschewing that nice custom component when an off the shelf one will do.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>Designing for Competent Users</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/competentusers/" type="text/html" />
            <id>https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/competentusers/</id>
            <updated>2020-09-29T03:05:00Z</updated>

            <summary type="html">A lot of engineering designs revolve around not allowing the user to “do dumb things”. Honestly, this is a great thing to do. There are many cases, especially in protective equipment that is a matter of life and death, where the potential for harm is far, far too high.</summary>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A lot of engineering designs revolve around not allowing the user to “do dumb things”. Honestly, this is a great thing to do. There are many cases, especially in protective equipment that is a matter of life and death, where the potential for harm is far, far too high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, legalism and holding human life as the highest good rather than something divine will always drag human life down, rather than lifting it up. We need danger. We need to afford people the chance to be competent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know this in certain senses automatically- it’s why bureaucracy has a bad name. It’s the exercise of rules designed to weed out bad decisions to the point where not only are good decisions weeded out as well, but the costs required are astronomical. Moldbug once quipped that bureacracies are based on the assumption that all particpants are actively seeking to defraud it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that societies work on trust. So why don’t we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we have that pesky word ‘user’? I really don’t think it’s apt. It puts in your head a sort of default, faceless being which could do any manner of stupid things. It isn’t a title. You don’t go around bestowing people or certifying ‘users’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more hopeful word might be ‘operator’. This implies that the person interacting with your apparatus should be competent, and can be trusted. Now, they might be a bad operator. That happens. But if you shift your mentality away from a ‘user’ (dumb, neutral-or-malificent, undignified) to a ‘bad operator’ (thinking (though wrong), good-intentioned, dignified but did their job wrong), you might start coming to their real level.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title>A Love Letter to Cardboard</title>
            <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/ode_to_cardboard/" type="text/html" />
            <id>https://blog.thadhughes.xyz/ode_to_cardboard/</id>
            <updated>2020-09-08T03:08:00Z</updated>

            <summary type="html">&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pVxldyIa0Bg&#34;&gt;Steel is the king of building materials. Plywood is the queen.&lt;/a&gt;</summary>
            <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pVxldyIa0Bg&#34;&gt;Steel is the king of building materials. Plywood is the queen.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/assets/images/cardboard.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A Love Letter to Cardboard&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no court is properly full without a jester.
The jester says things that should not be said. He predicts folly and demise to them, letting the repute of the king and queen go untarnished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cardboard comes in many flavors. Plain stock is effectively thick, brown paper. It cuts and folds easily, with little bias to grain direction.
Single wall board is the most common type. It&amp;rsquo;s corrugations provide strength from bending in one axis, but permit bends in the other direction. A blessing and a curse, this allows for some interesting construction methods.
Double wall board stacks two layers of corrugated material parallel to each other. This provides additional strength, and makes bending harder.
However, when the board learns of the queen&amp;rsquo;s ways, he may find ever more strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commercial overlords fear the power of an overpowered jester, and so seek to limit his power. But by stacking layers perpindicular, the court&amp;rsquo;s orthotropic member becomes less so- gaining complete out of plane fortitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of his utility is, of course, his replacability. But a jester is replaced only by another jester. His role is unparalleled. Creating large sheetmetal parts is costly and time-consuming, and plastic is only slightly less so. Cardboard can be cut quickly on a laser- nearly an order of magnitude faster than plywood. It can be cut with knife and welded with hot glue. Shaped, reformed, and thrown in the dungeon without penalty, and pulled off the streets for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While if he were to seize the throne, our world would turn to pulp&amp;hellip; he serves at hand and foot, keeping our kingdom from ruin.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        </entry>
    
</feed>
